Guide to the E.M. Warrick papers AD.MC.151
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
E.M. Warrick papers
1941-1959
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Warrick, E.M. (Edward Manley), 1924-2015
AD.MC.151
71 Photographic Slides in one metal box.
0.5 Linear Feet of files, in one document box.
Photographs, correspondence, reports, documents and ephemera, related to the military service of E.M. (Edward Manley) Warrick, a British Army officer assigned to the Royal Engineers, documenting his participation in the Jebel Akhdar war in Oman in 1958. In addition, the collection includes documents related to Warrick's training and initial service in the Middle East Forces in Palestine in 1946-1947.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, April 2025.
Arrangement
The E.M. Warrick papers are arranged in four series: 1. Middle East Land Forces, School of Military Engineering, 2. Oman, Jebel Akhdar War, 1958, 3. Publications and miscellany, and 4. Photographs. Aside from a couple of intact folders, there was no system of order in the papers at the time of acquisition, and the current system of arrangement was created by the processing archivist. The photographs, which were housed in a metal box with a written inventory, have been kept in the same order in which Warrick arranged them, matching his inventory and using his captions, save for the last several images, which either had no captions or were not represented on his inventory.
Biographical note
Edward Manley Warrick (1924-2015) was born on 21 August 1924 in Woolwich, Greater London. Few details about his biography are available other than those found in public records and sketched out in documents found in his archival collection.
It appears that Warrick spent his younger years living in Kent, as his mother, Mrs. E.M. Warrick, settled in or near Tunbridge Wells. At the time when Warrick joined the British Army, when he was granted leave he usually returned to Kent, but when he listed his mother as next-of-kin in documents from his military service in the Middle East in the late 1950s, she was listed as living in the West Country, in Weymouth, Dorset.
The records in this collection begin with Warrick's service in the Royal Engineers (23rd Field Company), while he was in transit from France to a training camp in Palestine in late 1945 or early 1946. He was commissioned as a 2nd Lieutenant on 5 August 1945, and according to the London Gazette, was promoted to the rank of Lieutenant in 1950, and the rank of full Captain in 1954. He retired with the rank of Major in August 1979.
Warrick's time in the Middle East began with at least a year or two in training (1946) at the Middle East Land Forces School of Military Engineering in Beit Nabala, Palestine. As an engineer in training, also known as a "sapper," his collection records activities related to the assembly and transport of military equipment, building of bridges and docks, location and removal of land mines, and related activities. During his time in training, he participated in exercises in and around Palestine and Transjordan.
While records are sparse, it appears that Warrick's later career had him based in Cyprus, East Africa, and perhaps Bahrain and Nepal, at a minimum. The existing archival collection was part of a larger collection of material from Warrick that included photographs and other materials documenting mountaineering expedition with other British Army personnel in East Africa (Mount Kenya, Mount Kilimanjaro) and Nepal (Mount Everest), leading to the supposition that his later career included training and practice in high-altitude warfare and mountain climbing. In 1958 he was called upon to travel from his base in Bahrain and participate in the Jebel Akhdar War, in which British forces came to the support of the Sultan of Muscat, Said bin Taimur, in his fight against insurgents loyal to the Imam Ghalib al-Hinai, who sought to control the interior of the country. As part of these activities, Warrick led a detachment that entered the mountains and placed mines and other explosive devices in wadis near the town of Nizwa, an operation that Warrick later referred to as "Operation Teddy Boy's Picnic" ("Teddy" being the nickname that Warrick used for himself, and "Teddy Boys" being a youth subculture in Britain from the 1950s, distinguished by its style of dress and reputation for violent brawling).
Little is known about Warrick's subsequent life and career, other than he appears to have married Janet Gobey in Abingdon in 1962, and after retirement, lived mostly in Yeovil, Somerset, where he died on 7 June 2015.
[sources: Ancestry.com, particularly Birth, Death, and Marriage registers for the U.K., and Electoral Rolls; as well as the London Gazette].
Content Description
The E.M. Warrick papers contain photographs, correspondence, reports, documents and ephemera, related to the military service of E.M. (Edward Manley) Warrick (1924-2015), a British Army officer assigned to the Royal Engineers, documenting his participation in the Jebel Akhdar war in Oman in 1958. In addition, the collection includes documents related to Warrick's training and initial service in the Middle East Forces in Palestine in 1946-1947.
The first, and largest, series in the collection, titled "Middle East Land Forces, School of Military Engineering," was created during the period when Warrick was sent for training at the school, located in Beit Nabala, Palestine. Much of the material relates to the training of engineers, often referred to as "sappers" in British military slang, and documents the experiences of Warrick as he gained experience in tasks such as the shipment of construction equipment, the construction of pontoon bridges and temporary structures for camps, and learning to defend against insurgents. Included are notes, movement orders, inventories of equipment, written examinations, and documents from training exercises, which taken together form a rough picture of the formation of such soldiers, who often followed combat troops in order to construct basic infrastructure such as roads, bridges, and shelter for troops in the aftermath of battles. Evidence that such training was not purely theoretical can be seen in reports and instructions from the commanding officer of Warrick's company, referencing armed attacks by unnamed insurgents, including one on a police command post that killed two police officers in April 1947, and instructions on identifying and removing landmines.
The next series of documents, titled "Oman, Jebel Akhdar War," records Warrick's experiences a decade later, when he was called to the interior of the Sultanate of Oman to take part in an operation against insurgents near Nizwa, at the base of the Jebel Akhdar mountain range, which included the laying of booby traps in the wadis and mountainous terrain. Documents in this series include a report from an expedition of Royal Engineers who were active in the same region the previous year, a list of personnel from Warrick's operation (with next of kin listed), a series of situation reports during the operation, and Warrick's own post-operation report and a letter of commendation from Warrick's commanding officer on the operation and subsequent activities of his squadron in Oman.
The third series, titled "Publications and Miscellany," includes printed booklets on map reading, as well as commemorative programs for events that Warrick attended, such as the victory celebration in London in June 1946 and a parade on the occasion of King George's birthday in June 1950. In addition, an issue of the military newspaper "Aden Calling" from November 1959 featured a front-page article about a climb of Mount Kilimanjaro by a group of British soldiers, which included Warrick, who was based in Nairobi by that time. Empty folders were included in this series because of the information they contained, both in relation to Warrick's activities with the Middle East Forces in Palestine and also one that contains his own title for the Jebel Akhdar operation that he led in 1958, "Operation Teddy Boy's Picnic."
The fourth, and last, series consists of photographic slides taken by Warrick during his time in Oman and Bahrain in late 1958, as well as his journey from the latter to his next posting in Nairobi, by way of Aden and Mombasa, presumably in late 1958 or early 1959. Accompanying the slides, which are color images enclosed in plastic and glass housings, is a handwritten list, with 70 images that are numbered and captioned. The first 51 images listed are from the Oman operation from September 1958, and the remaining images are from Bahrain, where Warrick was stationed at the time, and of his journey from there to his next post in Kenya, by way of Aden. All but four of the images are present, with the missing ones consisting of one of rebels in Oman (34.) and images of Warrick (51.), his commanding officer (50., Sgt. Curds) and a rebel chief (49). In addition to the images that are numbered and captioned are six additional images from his subsequent service in Kenya, and other unidentified locales, including a visit of the Queen Mother and a scene from Naivasha. In the finding aid, the captions are listed as Warrick wrote them on the slide frames and on his list, and where the captions on these two sources differ, both are added to the description.
Separated materials
This material was part of a larger group of documents from Warrick's estate, which were auctioned by Lawrence Auctioneers of Crewkerne, United Kingdom, in September 2024. Items were presumably split up and sold on the antiquarian market prior to the acquisition of these two groups of materials (photographs and papers) in April 2025. Materials that were auctioned in 2024, but which are not included in the current collection, include photographs, papers, and ephemera related to Warrick's subsequent military career, with an emphasis on his mountaineering activities in Kenya in the late 1950s and Nepal in the 1970s. It is not known where those materials currently are.
Oman -- History -- 20th century; Counterinsurgency -- Great Britain.; Oman -- History, Military -- 20th century; Great Britain -- Armed forces -- Palestine; Great Britain. Army. Royal Engineers; Great Britain. Army. Middle East Forces.
- Middle East Land Forces, School of Military Engineering, 1943-1951 (bulk 1946-1947)
  - Commanding Officer, 23rd Field Company: reports and orders concerning attacks, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Communications and orders, miscellaneous, 1946 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, general, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Demonstrations and parades, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Equipment, loading of, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Equipment, miscellaneous, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Examinations, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Greeting cards, 1946, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Land mines, 1946, and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Maps (of Palestine, plus hand-drawn map of troop positions), 1943 and undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mess (personal provisions), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Movement orders, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Organization chart and lists of personnel, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Recreation (ephemera), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reconnaisance, 1944-1945, and undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Structures, diagrams of (cookhouse, latrines), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Training, general, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Training exercises: "Bones" and "Insurgent", December 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Training exercises: "Beaver", December 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Travel and leaves of absence, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Oman (Jebel Akhdar War), 1957-1959
  - Report: "Chief Engineer Cyprus. A report on Muscat Operation. by Capt. V.F. Worlledge, R.E.", undated, circa August 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Report: "Report on the Laying of Booby Traps in the Oman, Sep to Oct 1958 by Capt. E.M. Warrick, R.E., Bahrain", October 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - List of personnel, with next of kin and religious affiliation, undated, circa August 1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Operational notes and diagrams (handwritten), 24 - 29 September 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Situation reports, September - October 1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Message of commendation, 7 August 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Publications and miscellany, 1941-1959
  - "Elementary Map Reading, 1941. Reprinted with Amendments (Nos. 1 to 3), 1943" (The War Office, November 1943), 1945 reprint (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Official Program of the Victory Celebrations" [London], 8th June 1946 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Annexes, Appendices & Maps to the Report by the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine to the General Assembly, Geneva, Switzerland, 31st August, 1947," London: H.M.S.O. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Celebration in London of the Birthday of His Majesty the King. Trooping the Colour on the Horse Guards Parade" (with ticket to event inserted in program), June 8th, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Aden Calling," Issue 231 [front-page article on ascent of Mount Kilimanjaro, featuring Warrick], November 1, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Empty folders, with markings ("Director of Works, M.E.F.", with list of contents not present, and "Teddy Boy's Picnic, Oman, 1958"), undated and 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ephemera, miscellaneous (photograph of friend, notes, instructions for use of detonator, service ribbon, calendar), 1947 and undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photographs
  - Oman, 1958
    - Arrival at Azeiba / Muscat Airp[or]t (Box 2, Image 1)
    - Airport, Muscat / Leaving airport (Box 2, Image 2)
    - Entrance to Muscat / Gate of Muscat (Box 2, Image 3)
    - Beit el Falluj camp (1) (Box 2, Image 4)
    - Beit el Falluj Camp (2) / Muscat well (Box 2, Image 5)
    - Convoy from Beit to Izki, 90 miles (1) / On convoy (Box 2, Image 6)
    - Convoy from Beit to Izki, 90 miles (2) / Half way (Box 2, Image 7)
    - Convoy from Beit to Izki, 90 miles (3) / En route (Box 2, Image 8)
    - Izki camp (Box 2, Image 9)
    - Support for Wadhai (Box 2, Image 10)
    - Taken under fire (Box 2, Image 11)
    - View north of Izki (Box 2, Image 12)
    - Troop swimming in Izki falluj (1) (Box 2, Image 13)
    - Troop swimming in Izki falluj (2) (Box 2, Image 14)
    - After storm at Izki camp (1) (Box 2, Image 15)
    - After storm at Izki camp (2) (Box 2, Image 16)
    - Izki life guards (Box 2, Image 17)
    - Booby traps at Wadhai (Box 2, Image 18)
    - Birkat al Mauz village and fort (1) (Box 2, Image 19)
    - Birkat al Mauz village and fort (2) (Box 2, Image 20)
    - Birkat al Mauz village and fort (3) (Box 2, Image 21)
    - Mined flail (Box 2, Image 22)
    - Route to Ruhbah (Box 2, Image 23)
    - Ruhbah well (Box 2, Image 24)
    - Rebel positions / Ruhbah (Box 2, Image 25)
    - Ruhbah boobies (Box 2, Image 26)
    - Mortar Wadi (1) (Box 2, Image 27)
    - Mortar Wadi (2) (Box 2, Image 28)
    - Kamah Wadi (1) (Box 2, Image 29)
    - Kamah Wadi (2) (Box 2, Image 30)
    - Kamah village (Box 2, Image 31)
    - Kamah camp (Box 2, Image 32)
    - Tanuf operation: softening up of rebels / Bombardment (1) (Box 2, Image 33)
    - Tanuf operation: softening up of rebels / Bombardment (2) [missing: not in box] (Box 2, Image [34])
    - En route / Operation Tanuf (Box 2, Image 35)
    - Near Tanuf (Box 2, Image 36)
    - Tanuf Wadi (Box 2, Image 37)
    - Arrival at Tanuf (Box 2, Image 38)
    - Tanuf village (Box 2, Image 39)
    - Finale / Tanuf finale (Box 2, Image 40)
    - Clearing camp (Box 2, Image 41)
    - Approach to Nizwa (Box 2, Image 42)
    - Nizwa outskirts (Box 2, Image 43)
    - Nizwa (Box 2, Image 44)
    - Nizwa Fort (Box 2, Image 45)
    - Nizwa natives (Box 2, Image 46)
    - Nizwa, last view (Box 2, Image 47)
    - Group picture [missing from box] (Box 2, Image [48])
    - Rebel chief [missing from box] (Box 2, Image [49])
    - Sgt. Curds [missing from box] (Box 2, Image [50])
    - Ted [missing from box] (Box 2, Image [51])
  - Bahrain, 1958
    - Refinery sunrise (Box 2, Image 52)
    - Twin minerets [sic] (Box 2, Image 53)
    - Dhobi spring (Box 2, Image 54)
    - Bahrain - Aden: H.M.S. Ceylon (Box 2, Image 55)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Sitra jetty (Box 2, Image 56)
    - Bahrain - Aden: last view of Bahrain (Box 2, Image 57)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Squadron at work on Ceylon (1) (Box 2, Image 58)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Squadron at work on Ceylon (2) (Box 2, Image 59)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Squadron at work on Ceylon (3) (Box 2, Image 60)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Bilsby on course (Box 2, Image 61)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Aden panorama / View of Aden (Box 2, Image 62)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Aden goats (Box 2, Image 63)
    - Bahrain - Aden: H.M.S. Puma (Box 2, Image 64)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Sqn. leave quay (Box 2, Image 65)
    - Bahrain - Aden: On way to Puma (Box 2, Image 66)
    - Bahrain - Aden: Embarkation (Box 2, Image 67)
    - On way to Mombasa (Box 2, Image 68)
    - Leaving Aden / On way to Mombasa (Box 2, Image 69)
    - Aden Harbour (Box 2, Image 70)
  - Kenya and unidentified locales, undated, circa 1959
    - Queen Mother (Box 2, Image 71)
    - Arrival at Naivasha (Box 2, Image 72)
    - Halt for lunch (Box 2, Image 73)
    - Gorge (Box 2, Image 74)
    - [unidentified, people on airstrip with plane] (Box 2, Image 75)
    - [unidentified, gateway to stone-walled compound] (Box 2, Image 76)